Catalog of the Walt Whitman Literary Manuscripts in the Walt Whitman Collection, Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center at the University of Texas at Austin
Published by The Walt Whitman Archive in collaboration with the University of Nebraska-Lincoln Libraries.
- Works, 1846-1913 and undated
  - The Tramp and Strike Questions, notes The tramp & strike questions, about 1882; tex.00311; xxx.00539; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 2, Folder 6)
    This page of notes about the problems of American capitalism is one of several manuscripts that Whitman wrote with the intention of delivering a lecture on what he called "the tramp and strike questions." Though the lecture never materialized, a short essay based on the manuscripts was published under the title The Tramp and Strike Questions. Part of a Lecture proposed, (never deliver'd.) in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–83 ). It was later reprinted in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
  - The Tramp and Strike Questions, notes Tramp & strike question, about 1882; tex.00312; xxx.00539; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 2, Folder 6)
    These notes, jotted with apparent haste, are part of the manuscript material Whitman generated with the intention of delivering a lecture on what he called "the tramp and strike questions." Though the lecture never materialized, a short essay based on the material was published under the title The Tramp and Strike Questions. Part of a Lecture proposed, (never deliver'd.) in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–83 ). It was later reprinted in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
  - Two men, apparently father and son on foot… [Two men, apparently father & son], between 1879 and 1882; tex.00313; xxx.00932; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Brief note that records an image from Whitman's 1879 trip through Missouri and Kansas and into Colorado. Whitman used this image in The Spanish Peaks—Evening on the Plains, which was first published in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–83 ) and later reprinted in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
  - Walt Whitman still remains in St. Louis, Missouri… [under Personal], 1879; tex.00315; xxx.00933; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Short press release, with several revisions, written sometime in the last three months of 1879, during Whitman's stay at St. Louis with his brother Jeff, following his train trip to Colorado. No newspaper printing of this note has been located. Much of the material here did appear, however, in the St. Louis Post-Dispatch on December 17, 1879, in an article titled Walt Whitman: What the Poet Does and How He Lives in St. Louis—Loafing and Inviting His Soul. See Jim McWilliams, An Unknown 1879 Profile of Whitman, Walt Whitman Quarterly Review 11.3 (1994), 141–143.
  - Song of Myself, [You villain, Touch!], about 1855; tex.00002; xxx.00048; poetry prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 2, Folder 1)
    One side of this manuscript features about eleven lines, heavily revised, for the poem eventually titled Song of Myself, beginning with You villain, Touch! The poem was first published in the 1855 first edition of Leaves of Grass. The notes on the other side, regarding prehistoric human life, are not known to be related to any of Whitman's published work.
  - Who shall write--who tell--who paint… [Who shall write], probably between 1855 and 1870; tex.00054; xxx.00707; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Fragment of approximately forty words, in which the poet writes that if he "were younger & well" he would write a book containing "the lessons of one mere day and night—the picture of the sky." No connection has been established between this manuscript and any of Whitman's published works.
  - Write a drunken song… Write A Drunken Song, probably between 1860 and 1875; tex.00055; xxx.00708; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Note containing twelve words, wherein Whitman suggests writing "A Drunken Song." The relationship of this manuscript to Whitman's published work is unknown.
  - Write a poem on the theme the great charge and repulse of the Secesh… [write a poem on the theme], between 1864 and 1890; tex.00056; xxx.00709; poetry prose 1 leaf handwritten printed (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Short handwritten note, approximately twenty words, accompanying two pasted-down newspaper clippings. It is unknown which newspaper or newspapers published these items. The accounts describe Major General Winfield Scott Hancock's repulse of the charge led by Major General George E. Pickett at Gettysburg. No definitive connections between this manuscript and Whitman's published work have been established.
  - [—while so many kings, generals, philosophers, poets], about 1888; tex.00203; xxx.00486; prose 1 leaf handwritten
    This manuscript fragment, written as a series of phrases interspersed with names and dates, is an early draft toward the introductory paragraph of Notes (such as they are) founded on Elias Hicks, an essay that was first published in November Boughs ( 1888 ) and later reprinted in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
  - [While the great composers Beethoven], about 1888; tex.00204; xxx.00486; prose 1 leaf handwritten
    This manuscript fragment is an early draft of material Whitman used in the introductory paragraph of Notes (such as they are) founded on Elias Hicks, an essay that was first published in November Boughs ( 1888 ) and later reprinted in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ). See also tex.00204, a closely related manuscript. The leaf has been pasted to a backing sheet, rendering the verso inaccessible.
  - [29th Mass.], about 1875; tex.00243; xxx.00925; prose 1 leaf handwritten
    The material in this one-page manuscript was used in the essay A Yankee Antique, which was first published in Memoranda during the War ( 1875–76 ) and later reprinted in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–83 ) and in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ). The leaf is pasted to a backing sheet, making the reverse side inaccesssible.
  - [—the Sacred Million], about 1875; tex.00244; xxx.00926; prose 1 leaf handwritten
    Several trial phrases regarding the "millions" killed during the Civil War. This material appeared in The Million Dead, too, summ'd up—The Unknown in Memoranda during the War ( 1875–76 ), an essay later reprinted as The Million Dead, Too, Summ'd Up in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–83 ) and Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ). The manuscript leaf is pasted to a backing sheet, making the reverse side inaccesssible.
  - [the fighting was Saturday night], about 1875; tex.00245; xxx.00902; prose 1 leaf handwritten
    Notes about the Battle of Chancellorsville and fragmentary draft material about the writing of Civil War histories. The draft material contributed to A Night Battle, over a week since in Memoranda during the War ( 1875–76 ), an essay later reprinted as A Night Battle, Over a Week Since in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–83 ) and in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ). The manuscript leaf is pasted to a backing sheet, making the reverse side inaccesssible.
  - [In an adjoining ward], about 1875; tex.00246; xxx.00927; prose 1 leaf handwritten
    Brief manuscript fragment related to Two Brothers, one South, one North—May 28–29 in Memoranda during the War ( 1875–76 ), an essay later reprinted as Two Brothers, One South, One North in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–83 ) and in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ). The manuscript leaf is pasted to a backing sheet, making the reverse side inaccesssible.
  - [He died almost], about 1875; tex.00248; xxx.00925; prose 1 leaf handwritten
    Manuscript fragment of several short sentences that contributed to the essay A Yankee Antique, which was first published in Memoranda during the War ( 1875–76 ) and later reprinted in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–83 ) and in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ). The leaf is pasted to a backing sheet, making the reverse side inaccesssible.
  - [Private Stewart C. Glover], about 1875; tex.00249; xxx.00928; prose 1 leaf handwritten
    One manuscript leaf, inscribed on both sides, describing a young soldier who died after being wounded during the Battle of the Wilderness during the Civil War. Most of the writing is in an unknown hand, possibly that of "R. H. Foote," whose name appears on the manuscript. The text of this manuscript contributed to Death of a Hero, which was first published in Memoranda during the War in 1875–76 and later reprinted in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–83 ) and in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
  - Serg't Harlowe, about 1875; tex.00250; xxx.00925; prose 1 leaf handwritten
    Brief notes about Calvin Harlowe, a Civil War soldier whose death Whitman described in A Yankee Antique, an essay first published in Memoranda during the War ( 1875–76 ) and later reprinted in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–83 ) and in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ). The leaf is pasted to a backing sheet, making the reverse side inaccesssible.
  - [for introductory to], probably between 1868 and 1876; tex.00251; xxx.00524; xxx.00502; prose 1 leaf handwritten
    Fragmentary draft of an introductory essay that was apparently never published. The note at the top suggests that it was intended for some version of Democratic Vistas, which was first published in 1871, or of Memoranda during the War, which was first published in 1875–76. The idea expressed in this manuscript occurs frequently in Whitman's published writings, though never in these particular phrases.
  - [WW's Nov. Boughs], about 1890; tex.00272; xxx.00410; prose 1 leaf handwritten
    A one-page draft of a footnote for A Backward Glance O'er Travel'd Roads, which was first published in the so-called deathbed edition of Leaves of Grass in 1891. Although Whitman created the essay from several previously published pieces, the note inscribed on this manuscript had not appeared in print before.
  - [Elias Hicks], about 1888; tex.00273; xxx.00486; prose 1 leaf handwritten
    Brief notes on the reigns of Frederick the Great and King George III, labelled for use in Notes (such as they are) founded on Elias Hicks, an essay that was first published in November Boughs ( 1888 ) and later reprinted in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
  - Two Brooklyn boys., about 1882; tex.00289; xxx.00929; prose 1 leaf handwritten
    Draft of Two Brooklyn Boys, a short piece published in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–83 ) and reprinted in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
  - [Among the things arising out], about 1874; tex.00298; xxx.00930; prose 3 leaves handwritten
    Three-page draft, heavily revised, of Still More of the Hospitals, a section of the article 'Tis But Ten Years Since. (Fourth Paper.), published in the New York Weekly Graphic on February 21, 1874. Further revised, it was later published in Memoranda during the War ( 1875–76 ) as Aug., Sep., and Oct., '63—The Hospitals. Finally, it appeared as Hospitals Ensemble in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–83 ) and in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
  - [Then Principal], about 1881; tex.00303; xxx.00529; prose 1 leaf handwritten
    Two scraps, pasted together, on which are inscribed a heavily revised, partial draft of the essay first published as The Poetry of the Future in the February 12, 1881, issue of the North American Review. Whitman later revised and republished the essay as Poetry To-Day in America—Shakspere—The Future in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–83 ). It also appeared in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
  - [Not free and naive poetry], about 1881; tex.00304; xxx.00529; prose 1 leaf handwritten
    Manuscript fragment of the essay first published as The Poetry of the Future in the February 12, 1881, issue of the North American Review. Whitman later revised and republished the essay as Poetry To-Day in America—Shakspere—The Future in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–83 ). It also appeared in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ). The leaf has been pasted to a backing sheet, rendering the verso inaccessible.
  - [Two powerful & perhaps paradoxical], about 1876; tex.00314; xxx.00533; prose 1 leaf handwritten
    The idea that democracy includes the two seemingly opposite forces of individualism and group identity, expressed in this manuscript fragment, can be found in many of Whitman's published works. The comparison to centrifugal and centripetal physical forces suggests that this manuscript possibly contributed to Nationality—(and Yet.), which was first published in Two Rivulets ( 1876 ). It was later republished in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–83 ) and in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ). The leaf has been pasted to a backing sheet, rendering the verso inaccessible.
  - The Army Hospitals, 1863; tex.00288; xxx.00900; xxx.00901; prose 1 leaf handwritten
    Partial manuscript draft of an essay about the Civil War army hospitals. From it's relationship with another manuscript now at the University of Virginia (tex.00097), it is clear that this manuscript represents a prepublication stage of the article The Great Army of the Sick, which was published in the New-York Times on February 26, 1863. Whitman later used a part of the published article (a part that has no parallel in the present manuscript) for the one-paragraph description of the Patent Office Hospital in Memoranda During the War ( 1875–76 ), labelled Feb. 23. The paragraph later appeared as Patent-Office Hospital in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–1883 ) and in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ). Whitman's revision of the title (which he made by cutting the top of the leaf, turning it over, and writing a new title) indicates both that he originally imagined this to be the first of a series of articles and that the present manuscript was intended to serve as a printer's copy.
  - [Already as I write], between 1872 and 1875; tex.00242; xxx.00940; xxx.00527; prose 1 leaf handwritten
    Manuscript, heavily revised, made from four scraps of paper. Two of the scraps (the second and fourth) were inscribed before being cut apart to insert the material on the third scrap. This manuscript seems to have been created over a period of at least several years, as Whitman used it for two different published pieces. It contributed to the Preface of As a Strong Bird on Pinions Free. And Other Poems ( 1872 ), which was reprinted as Preface, 1872, to "As a Strong Bird on Pinions Free," (now "Thou Mother with thy Equal Brood," in permanent ed'n.) in Two Rivulets ( 1876 ), Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–83 ), and Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ). It also contributed to a piece titled The War, though with two sides, really ONE IDENTITY (as struggles, furious conflicts of Nature, for final harmony.)—The Soil it bred and ripen'd from—the North as responsible for it as the South that appeared in the Notes section of Memoranda During the War ( 1875–76 ). This piece was also reprinted in Two Rivulets ( 1876 ).
  - [to start upon], between 1864 and 1874; tex.00247; xxx.00941; xxx.00942; prose 1 leaf handwritten
    This manuscript fragment was originally part of a larger leaf which comprised two other fragments as well: tex.00308 and tex.00297. Before the sheet was cut into three pieces, this fragment formed the lower part. The writing it contains is related to a section headed Fifty Army Hospitals Here—1863—Spring, a section of the article 'Tis But Ten Years Since. (Fourth Paper.), published in the New York Weekly Graphic on February 21, 1874. Further revised, it was later published in Memoranda during the War ( 1875–76 ) as Hospital Perplexity. This was reprinted in Two Rivulets ( 1876 ), Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–83 ), and Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
  - [to start upon], between 1864 and 1874; tex.00297; xxx.00930; xxx.00942; prose 1 leaf handwritten
    This manuscript fragment was originally part of a larger leaf which comprised two other fragments as well: tex.00308 and tex.00247. Before the sheet was cut into three pieces, this fragment formed the upper part. The writing it contains is related to a section headed Specimen of the Army Hospitals Now in and around Washington in Our Wounded and Sick Soldiers, an article published in the December 11, 1864 issue of the New York Times. Whitman also used this material in Still More of the Hospitals, a section of the article 'Tis But Ten Years Since. (Fourth Paper.), published in the New York Weekly Graphic on February 21, 1874. Further revised, it was later published in Memoranda during the War ( 1875–76 ) as Aug., Sep., and Oct., '63—The Hospitals. This was reprinted, unchanged, in Two Rivulets ( 1876 ). Finally, it appeared as Hospitals Ensemble in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–83 ) and in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
    It is uncertain whether Whitman created this manuscript as he drafted material for the 1864 article or wrote it as he worked to synthesize earlier pieces for the 'Tis But Ten Years Since series, though the latter scenario is more likely.
  - [They are frequently changed], between 1864 and 1874; tex.00308; xxx.00941; xxx.00942; prose 1 leaf handwritten
    This manuscript fragment was originally part of a larger leaf which comprised two other fragments as well: tex.00297 and tex.00247. Before the sheet was cut into three pieces, this fragment formed the middle part. The writing it contains is related to a section headed Fifty Army Hospitals Here—1863—Spring, a section of the article 'Tis But Ten Years Since. (Fourth Paper.), published in the New York Weekly Graphic on February 21, 1874. Further revised, it was later published in Memoranda during the War ( 1875–76 ) as Hospital Perplexity. This was reprinted in Two Rivulets ( 1876 ), Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–83 ), and Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
  - For Dem Vistas, 1882 or before; tex.00458; xxx.00505; xxx.00998; prose 1 leaf handwritten
    A brief paragraph suggesting that the unifying motif of a projected volume of miscellaneous prose pieces should be various aspects of nature viewed from the perspective of democracy. Although Whitman eventually titled his collection Specimen Days ( 1882–83 ), the present manuscript uses the working title Mulleins & Bumble Bees, one of many that he considered over the rather long period during which he contemplated publication. In Cedar-Plums—Names, one of the short essays in the collection, he discusses some of his difficulties with coherence and titling.